<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>java on Codeklutz</title>
    <link>https://codeklutz.com/tags/java/</link>
    <description>Recent content in java on Codeklutz</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://codeklutz.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 23:49:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://codeklutz.com/tags/java/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Which would you go for? Spring boot cron job,scheduled tasks vs Events in Mysql.</title>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/posts/which-would-you-go-for-spring-boot-cron-jobscheduled-tasks-vs-events-in-mysql/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 23:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://codeklutz.com/posts/which-would-you-go-for-spring-boot-cron-jobscheduled-tasks-vs-events-in-mysql/</guid>
      <description>I was recently studying about using cron jobs in spring boot for a particular use case for my small side project. I ended up not using the cron job but rather went the SQL way(will explain this in detail below). However,in the process I learnt a lot about cron jobs and scheduling in spring boot so this is just a small article about my learnings.
But first I shall tell you a little about my use case and why I thought about cron jobs in the first place….</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Polymorphism in Java</title>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/posts/polymorphism-in-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 23:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://codeklutz.com/posts/polymorphism-in-java/</guid>
      <description>Just revisiting and explaining myself Polymorphism concept here through a blog post. The words Polymorphism means multiple forms.
In Java ,Polymorphism means multiple forms of an object. We shall divide this article into 3 sections.
1.Syntax
2.Calling a variable polymorphically.
3.Calling a method polymorphically.
1.SyntaxPermalink Now in polymorphism in Java, the thumb key rule to remember is
super = subPermalink Meaning the variable reference (LHS) must always be a super class reference and the object initialization(RHS) must a sub class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How constructors work in Java</title>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/posts/how-constructors-work-in-java/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 21:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://codeklutz.com/posts/how-constructors-work-in-java/</guid>
      <description>Constructors are used every time to initialize instance variables. There are some additional rules associated with constructors that are often asked in interviews.Hence revising those here through a blog post.
A constructor is used to initialize instance variables When an object of an class is created,JVM goes to the class and searches for that matching constructor.If Constructor is NOT PRESENT it gives a compile error. By default every class has a constructor called default no argument constructor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
