<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>journey on Codeklutz</title>
    <link>https://codeklutz.com/tags/journey/</link>
    <description>Recent content in journey on Codeklutz</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://codeklutz.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 21:41:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://codeklutz.com/tags/journey/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title> My First Tech Talk: The Journey from Panic to Presentation</title>
      <link>https://codeklutz.com/posts/my-first-tech-talk-the-journey-from-panic-to-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 21:41:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://codeklutz.com/posts/my-first-tech-talk-the-journey-from-panic-to-presentation/</guid>
      <description>My First Tech Talk: The Journey from Panic to Presentation I recently had an opportunity to give a technical talk at GitTogether Mumbai. This is a small blog post based on my experience of giving a talk and a little behind-the-scenes turmoil written as a blog post.
##How Do You Secure a Speaking Slot?
This was the big question! It took me countless applications, several rejections, and a sprinkle of luck.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="my-first-tech-talk-the-journey-from-panic-to-presentation">My First Tech Talk: The Journey from Panic to Presentation</h1>
<p>I recently had an opportunity to give a technical talk at GitTogether Mumbai. This is a small blog post based on my experience of giving a talk and a little behind-the-scenes turmoil written as a blog post.</p>
<p>##How Do You Secure a Speaking Slot?</p>
<p>This was the big question! It took me countless applications, several rejections, and a sprinkle of luck. The trick? Pitch a talk that fits what the audience and organizers are looking for—it&rsquo;s all about relevance.</p>
<h2 id="what-happens-after-my-talk-was-selected">What happens after my talk was selected?</h2>
<p>The talk has been selected &hellip;&hellip;so now what?
The Panic strikes through!!
But so does the cycle of preparation&hellip;&hellip;</p>
<p>![GitTogether Tech Talk](/img/Screenshot 2024-10-02 at 21.14.56.png)</p>
<h2 id="will-they-find-it-interesting">Will They Find It Interesting?</h2>
<p>Creating a talk is one thing, delivering it in a way that keeps the audience engaged is another.
Once the panic and excitement strikes through so does the preparation. Preparing the contents for a talk is very different from presenting it. The information you INTEND to convey has to reach the audience in a way they perceive it and it has to be relatable and interesting for them to continue to listen!</p>
<h2 id="feedback-feedback-feedback-and-continuous-feedback">Feedback Feedback Feedback and Continuous Feedback!</h2>
<p>Ah yes, feedback—every speaker’s best friend (and occasional frenemy). It’s the secret sauce to leveling up your presentation, and trust me, you’ll need lots of it! I took every nugget of constructive criticism and tweaked my talk like a codebase on release day.</p>
<p>Now, let’s talk demos. the ultimate double-edged sword. Engineers love them but for presenters? A living nightmare! And guess what? I willingly walked into that nightmare. Yep, I gave a demo!</p>
<p>Why? Well, demos are like live-action thrillers—great for the audience but full of nerve-wracking moments for the speaker. Something is bound to go wrong (and spoiler: it did). Cue the sweaty palms and heart palpitations as things start to go wrong! But hey, the key is to stay calm, crack a joke or two, and power through the glitches.</p>
<p>In hindsight, the demo could’ve been smoother, but for my first big talk, it wasn’t a complete disaster. Want to witness the chaos? Here’s the link to the demo fail <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j_D0SG0yMEk">Link</a> I’m open to feedback (and maybe a little sympathy)!</p>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Every developer should experience the thrill of presenting their work to an appreciative public audience. It&rsquo;s more than just sharing your knowledge—it’s a chance to push your limits, boost your confidence, and ignite a deeper passion for learning. Stepping onto that stage changes the way you see yourself as a developer, fueling your drive to grow and evolve. Plus, there’s nothing quite like the energy of connecting with others and realizing how far you’ve come on your journey!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
